Register of the Milton Friedman papers 77011.4088897
Hoover Institution Archives
- Academic Career, 1939-1976 (Boxes 75-80)
  - University of Chicago, 1946-1976
    - Student doctoral theses (under the direction of Milton Friedman) and papers (under the direction of other professors) (Box-folder 80: 1)
      Includes correspondence.
    - Studies, "The Role of the Monetary and Banking System in the Business Cycle" (under the direction of Milton Friedman), research project description, 1951 (Box-folder 80: 2)
    - Subject file
      - 4E Contract [and faculty income], 1947-1950 (Box-folder 80: 3)
        Correspondence, notes, comments, memoranda, petitions, reports, and resolutions.
      - Ingersoll Foundation Fellowships, letter from D. Gale Johnson (Box-folder 80: 4)
      - Milton Friedman Fund, proposal and correspondence, 1976 (Box-folder 80: 5)
      - Teaching of economic theory, memoranda, 1946 (Box-folder 80: 6)
      - Teaching of statistics, memoranda, 1948 (Box-folder 80: 7)
    - Syllabi by others, 1950-1951 (Box-folder 80: 8)
- Subject File, 1939-1979 (Boxes 81-101)
  Memoranda, minutes, reports, studies, correspondence, and printed matter, arranged alphabetically by topic.
  - Aldine Publishing Company, 1964-1967 (Box-folder 81: 1)
    Correspondence, financial statements, and production schedules.
  - American Conservative Union, 1965-1966 (Box-folder 81: 2)
    Correspondence, memoranda, newsletters, reports, and statements.
  - American Economic Association, correspondence and memoranda, 1973-1976 (Box-folder 81: 3)
  - American Statistical Association, 1948 (Box-folder 81: 4)
    Correspondence, notes, memoranda, and draft constitution.
  - Bliss, C. I., typescript and printed writings, 1942 (Box-folder 81: 5)
    Includes reading notes by Milton Friedman and notes on related topics.
  - Cowles Commission, 1947 (Box-folder 81: 6)
    Memorandum by J. Marschak to the members of the Advisory Committee to the Cowles Commission and papers presented before the joint meeting of the American Economic Association and the Econometric Society.
  - Crane, Dwight B., referee's comments on his paper, "The Role of Banking Services in Corporation Demand Deposits,", undated (Box-folder 81: 7)
  - Cuban Center for Studies on Freedom, brochure, 1963 (Box-folder 81: 8)
  - Economics
    - Methodology and theory, journal articles, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 81: 9)
      For Milton Friedman's methodology, see also CORRESPONDENCE, Christenson, Charles; Lakatos, Imre; Latsis, Spiro J.
    - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 81: 10)
  - Energy - Petroleum, magazine article, 1979 (Box-folder 81: 11)
  - Eurodollars, journal articles, 1966-1974 (Box-folder 81: 12)
    See also CORRESPONDENCE, Bartley, Robert L. (Wall Street Journal).
  - Europe, 1950 (Box-folder 81: 13)
    Milton Friedman's memoranda, including to the Economic Cooperation Administration, Office of the United States Special Representative in Europe.
  - Federal Reserve Bank, studies, 1962-1965 (Box-folder 81: 14)
  - Federal Reserve System, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 82: 1)
    Correspondence, memoranda, reports, studies, and bibliography on money supply.
  - Finland, article by Albert Hunold, 1961 (Box-folder 82: 2)
  - Ford Foundation, correspondence with Thomas H. Carroll (University of North Carolina), 1952-1953 (Box-folder 82: 3)
    Includes digest of replies to the report of the Advisory Group to the Ford Foundation on Economics and the Behavioral Sciences.
  - Foundation for Economic Education, 1947-1954 (Box-folder 82: 4-5)
    Brochures, pamphlets, and newsletters.
  - Free Society Association, memoranda and newsletters, 1965-1967 (Box-folder 82: 6)
  - Germany - Economy, pamphlet, 1959 (Box-folder 82: 7)
  - Great Plains Legal Foundation, correspondence and newsletter, 1977 (Box-folder 82: 8)
  - Indexation and taxation, 1971-1975 (Box-folder 83: 1-5)
    Studies, reports, and correspondence.
  - Institute of Mathematical Statistics
    - General (Box-folder 84: 1)
    - Reports by Milton Friedman and others on the place of statistics in the university and the teaching of statistics, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 84: 2)
    - Correspondence, including with Harold Hotelling, chairman of the Institute's Committee on the Teaching of Statistics, 1945-1947 (Box-folder 84: 3)
      Includes a list of statisticians for consideration for appointment at the University of Chicago.
  - Israel, 1976-1977 (Box-folder 84: 4)
    Studies, data, journal articles, correspondence, and notes.
  - Japanese Economic Mission to the United States, brochure and correspondence, 1964 (Box-folder 84: 5)
  - Journal of Political Economy, 1947-1949 (Box-folder 84: 6)
    Correspondence, memoranda, and proposal.
  - Little, I., 1951 (Box-folder 84: 7)
    Notes by Milton Friedman and statement by Edward Mishan on I. Little, "Reformulation of Consumer's Behavior."
  - Machlup, Fritz, clipping, 1961 (Box-folder 84: 8)
  - Marshall, Alfred, photocopy of letter to Mr. Webb, 1897 (Box-folder 84: 9)
  - Medical research, journal article, 1965 (Box-folder 84: 10)
  - Monetary policy, 1947-1979
    Studies, discussion papers, reports, journal articles.
    - General (Box-folder 84: 11-12)
    - International (Box-folder 84: 13)
  - Mont Pélerin Society
    - General (Box-folder 85: 1)
    - Articles of incorporation, 1947 (Box-folder 85: 2)
    - Bibliography of publications by members, 1953 (Box-folder 85: 3)
    - Bylaws, 1964 (Box-folder 85: 4)
    - Circulars, 1947-1955 (Box-folder 85: 5)
    - Correspondence
      Includes memoranda and minutes.
      - Alphabetical file, 1959-1980
        - A-G (Box-folder 85: 6)
        - H (Box-folder 85: 7)
        - I-L (Box-folder 85: 8)
        - M-Z (Box-folder 85: 9)
      - Chronological file
        - 1946-1959 (Box-folder 86: 1)
        - 1960 (Box-folder 86: 2)
        - 1961
          - January-September (Box-folder 86: 3)
          - October-December (Box-folder 86: 4)
        - 1962 (Box-folder 86: 5)
        - 1963 (Box-folder 86: 6)
        - 1964 (Box-folder 86: 7)
        - 1965 (Box-folder 86: 8)
        - 1966 (Box-folder 86: 9)
        - 1967 (Box-folder 86: 10)
        - 1968 (Box-folder 86: 11)
        - 1969-1970 (Box-folder 86: 12)
        - 1971 (Box-folder 87: 1)
        - 1972-1977 (Box-folder 87: 2)
      - Re incorporation, 1947-1950 (Box-folder 87: 3)
      - Re fundraising, 1971-1972 (Box-folder 87: 4)
        See also Correspondence, Chronological file, 1961 and 1962.
    - Directories, 1949-1975 (Box-folder 87: 5)
    - Financial reports, 1957-1964 (Box-folder 87: 6)
    - Memorandum of association, 1947 (Box-folder 87: 7)
    - Newsletters, 1972-1979 (Box-folder 87: 8)
    - Notes (Box-folder 87: 9)
    - Proceedings of general meetings
      - 1947 (Box-folder 87: 10)
        Also includes a document from a free market study conference at the University of Chicago in 1948.
      - 1949 (Box-folder 87: 11)
      - 1951 (Box-folder 87: 12)
      - 1953 (Box-folder 87: 13)
      - 1954 (Box-folder 87: 14)
      - 1956 (Box-folder 87: 15)
      - 1957 (Box-folder 87: 16)
      - 1957 (Box-folder 88: 1)
      - 1958 (Box-folder 88: 2)
      - 1959 (Box-folder 88: 3)
      - 1960 (Box-folder 88: 4)
      - 1961 (Box-folder 88: 5-8)
      - 1962 (Box-folder 88: 9)
      - 1964 (Box-folder 88: 10)
      - 1965 (Box-folder 88: 11)
      - 1966 (Box-folder 88: 12)
      - 1968 (Box-folder 88: 13)
    - Quarterly journals, 1959-1962 (Box-folder 88: 14)
    - Reports, 1962-1972 (Box-folder 88: 15)
  - Moulton, H. G., reading notes, undated (Box-folder 88: 16)
  - National Academy of Sciences, correspondence and newsletter, 1973 (Box-folder 88: 17)
  - National Bureau of Economic Research
    - Calculations, undated (Box-folder 89: 1)
    - Comments by Anna J. Schwartz on Phillip D. Cagan, "A Theory of Monetary Effects on Interest Rates," and cover letter from Milton Friedman to F. Thomas Juster, 1969 (Box-folder 89: 2)
    - Correspondence
      - General
        - 1941-1959 (Box-folder 89: 3)
        - 1960 (Box-folder 89: 4)
        - 1961 (Box-folder 89: 5)
        - 1962 (Box-folder 89: 6)
        - 1963-1966 (Box-folder 89: 7)
      - Cagan, Phillip D., 1954-1955 (Box-folder 89: 8)
      - Carson, William J., 1954-1963 (Box-folder 89: 9)
      - Crayne, Susan, 1969 (Box-folder 89: 10)
        Includes her comments on Irving Fisher's work.
      - Easterlin, Richard A., 1958-1959 (Box-folder 89: 11)
      - Eisenpress, Harry, 1951 (Box-folder 89: 12)
      - Fabricant, Solomon, 1949-1964 (Box-folder 89: 13)
      - Fordham University Press, 1959-1961 (Box-folder 89: 14)
        Includes correspondence with Joseph R. Cammarosano.
      - Juster, F. Thomas, 1958-1959 (Box-folder 89: 15)
      - Mack, Ruth P., 1954-1955 (Box-folder 89: 16)
      - Moore, Geoffrey H., 1948-1964 (Box-folder 89: 17)
      - Schwartz, Anna J.
        Includes research material.
        - 1948 (Box-folder 90: 1)
        - 1949 (Box-folder 90: 2)
        - 1950-1951 (Box-folder 90: 3)
        - 1951-1954 (Box-folder 90: 4)
        - 1952 (Box-folder 90: 5)
        - 1953 (Box-folder 90: 6)
        - 1954 (Box-folder 90: 7)
        - 1955 (Box-folder 90: 8)
        - 1956 (Box-folder 91: 1)
        - 1957-1959 (Box-folder 91: 2)
        - 1960-1964 (Box-folder 91: 3)
        - 1965 (Box-folder 91: 4)
        - 1966-1967 (Box-folder 91: 5)
        - 1968-1969 (Box-folder 91: 6)
        - 1970-1971 (Box-folder 91: 7)
        - 1972-1975 (Box-folder 91: 8)
        - 1976-1978 (Box-folder 91: 9)
      - Wehle, Mark, 1957 (Box-folder 91: 10)
    - Lists of members attending the Conferences on Research in Income and Wealth, 1943-1945 (Box-folder 92: 1)
    - Memoranda
      - Milton Friedman on Wassily Leontief's manuscript, 1939 (Box-folder 92: 2)
      - Anna J. Schwartz on David K. Sheppard's United Kingdom money estimates, undated (Box-folder 92: 3)
    - Notes, data, research material
      - 1964-1965 (Box-folder 92: 4)
      - Analysis of cycles in call-date series polygon and step methods (Box-folder 92: 5)
      - Demand equations (Box-folder 92: 6)
      - Money and interest rates (Box-folder 92: 7)
      - Money supply (Box-folder 92: 8-11)
      - Net obligations of the government, 1958 (Box-folder 92: 12)
        Includes correspondence with Anna J. Schwartz and Phillip D. Cagan.
      - Rates of change
        - Money supply, 1956 (Box-folder 93: 1)
        - Clearings-debits and personal income, 1958 (Box-folder 93: 2)
      - Spectral analysis (Box-folder 93: 3)
      - Miscellaneous (Box-folder 93: 4)
    - Report by Milton Friedman on the Workshop in Money and Banking, undated (Box-folder 93: 5)
    - Studies
      - "Call Date Series of Deposits at All Banks in the United States, 1917-1946,", 1948-1951
        - General (Box-folder 93: 6)
        - Notes and correspondence with Henry C. Murphy, Anna J. Schwartz, Walter W. Stewart, Ralph A. Young, 1948-1950 (Box-folder 93: 7-8)
        - Notes and correspondence with Harry Eisenpress and Millard Hastay, 1949-1951 (Box-folder 94: 1)
      - "Monetary Factors in Business Cycles" (also called "Banking Study"), 1948-1973
        - General (Box-folder 94: 2-3)
        - Bibliographies and reading notes (Box-folder 94: 4)
        - Research material, including papers by Anna J. Schwartz and others (Box-folder 94: 5)
        - Charts, graphs, computer printouts (Box-folder 94: 6-9)
        - Notes and correspondence with Harry Eisenpress, Millard Hastay, Geoffrey H. Moore, Anna J. Schwartz, Hanna Stern, Robert Warren
          - Undated (Box-folder 95: 1-2)
            Includes partial typescript.
          - 1948-1951 (Box-folder 95: 3)
          - 1957-1960 (Box-folder 95: 4)
          - 1959-1960 (Box-folder 95: 5)
          - 1961-1963 (Box-folder 95: 6)
          - 1963 (Box-folder 96: 1)
          - 1968 (Box-folder 96: 2)
          - 1971 (Box-folder 96: 3)
          - 1972 (Box-folder 96: 4)
          - 1974 (Box-folder 96: 5)
      - "Pension,", 1958 (Box-folder 96: 6)
        Research material, typescript of material for participants of the Pension Study Advisory Committee, and letter from William J. Carson.
      - "Interest Rate,", 1961 (Box-folder 96: 7)
        Research material, progress report, and correspondence.
  - National Resources Committee
    - Notes and writings by Milton Friedman
      Includes some background material.
      - 1936 (Box-folder 97: 1)
      - 1937 (Box-folder 97: 2)
    - Studies
      Includes some background materials and material from the National Science Foundation.
      - "Ammain Scales,", 1935 September 25 (Box-folder 97: 3)
        Notes, bibliography, and memorandum by Milton Friedman.
      - "Family Types," notes and memoranda by Milton Friedman and others, 1935-1936 (Box-folder 97: 4)
      - "Consumption of Goods and Services by American Families,", 1935-1937
        See also: SPEECHES AND WRITINGS, "A Method of Comparing Incomes of Families Differing in Composition," 1950 June 9-11.
        - General (Box-folder 97: 5)
        - Forms (Box-folder 97: 6)
        - Memoranda by Milton Friedman, 1935-1939 (Box-folder 97: 7-8)
        - Notes and charts (Box-folder 97: 9-10)
          Includes some typescripts.
        - Statistical tables, 1936 (Box-folder 97: 11)
  - National Science Foundation, 1960-1961 (Box-folder 97: 12)
    Correspondence, memoranda, and research proposals.
  - Office of Scientific Research and Development, circulars and correspondence, 1946 (Box-folder 97: 13)
  - Philadelphia Society, bylaws, membership lists, and newsletters, 1966-1977 (Box-folder 98: 1)
  - President's Commission on an All-Volunteer Armed Force, 1972-1973 (Box-folder 98: 2)
    Contents of this folder do not match the original folder title. Contains correspondence with Anna Schwartz and notes relating to variability analysis of personal income.
  - President's Commission on National Goals, 1960, 1971 (Box-folder 98: 3)
    Folder contents do not match original folder title. Contains memoranda, minutes, speeches, and studies related to US monthly money rate of change.
  - President's Commission on White House Fellows, 1971-1974 (Box-folder 98: 4)
    Correspondence, membership lists, circulars, and reports.
  - Principles of Freedom
    - General
      Includes correspondence, financial reports, memoranda, and minutes.
      - 1962-1963 (Box-folder 98: 5)
      - 1964 (Box-folder 98: 6)
      - 1965-1967 (Box-folder 98: 7)
      - 1969-1973 (Box-folder 98: 8)
    - Typescript, "Capitalism and Federalism" (collective work by Principles of Freedom members), undated (Box-folder 99: 1-3)
  - Rent control, 1946-1951 (Box-folder 99: 4)
    Newsletters, brochures, correspondence, and clippings.
  - Rhodesia and South Africa, 1967-1976 (Box-folder 99: 5)
    Correspondence, notes, speeches, studies, and magazine article.
  - Samuelson, Paul A., 1950 (Box-folder 99: 6)
    Paper and correspondence with William J. Baumol and Leonard J. Savage, and letter from Riley Clay Sprowls to Milton Friedman.
  - Schultz, Henry, printed copies of writings, 1931-1935 (Box-folder 99: 7)
  - Smith, Adam, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 99: 8)
    Speeches, papers, articles, and clippings relating to Adam Smith's centennial celebration.
  - Social security
    - Correspondence, notes, papers, and journal articles, 1965-1979 (Box-folder 99: 9)
    - Publications, 1963-1971 (Box-folder 100: 1)
  - Soviet Union, 1948-1959 (Box-folder 100: 2)
    Pamphlets, speeches, and press release.
  - Statistical Research Group, bibliographies and research papers, 1946 (Box-folder 100: 3)
  - Statistics, 1933-1948 (Box-folder 100: 4)
    Papers, journal articles, course outlines, and clippings.
  - Tax limitation
    - General, 1964-1978 (Box-folder 100: 5-6)
      Correspondence, articles, newsletters, and memoranda. Includes publications of the National Tax Limitation Committee.
    - California, 1973 (Box-folder 100: 7)
      Legislative proposals, remarks, reports, press releases, and articles.
    - Illinois, 1975 (Box-folder 100: 8)
      Correspondence, resolutions, and press releases.
    - Michigan, correspondence and press releases, 1974-1976 (Box-folder 100: 9)
    - New Hampshire and Vermont, 1976 (Box-folder 100: 10)
      Correspondence, studies, newsletters, and clippings.
    - Other states, 1976-1978 (Box-folder 100: 11)
      Article, brochure, and report.
  - Teachers' Insurance and Annuity Association of America and College Retirement Equities Fund, 1946-1968 (Box-folder 101: 1)
    Correspondence, minutes, and reports.
  - United Kingdom, discussion paper and journal article, 1969-1971 (Box-folder 101: 2)
  - United States
    - Economy
      - General
        - Memoranda, surveys, estimates (1929-1942), 1941-1942 (Box-folder 101: 3)
        - Speech by Walter Hoadley on American business and public policy research, 1982 (Box-folder 101: 4)
      - Minimum wage laws and unemployment among African-American teenagers, fact sheet and clipping, 1964 (Box-folder 101: 5)
        See also: CORRESPONDENCE, Striner, Herbert E.
      - Monetary policy, 1951 (Box-folder 101: 6)
        Correspondence, notes, memoranda, clippings, and statements by Theodore W. Schultz and John D. Clark before the United States Congress Joint Economic Committee.
      - Poverty-combatting programs, fact sheet, 1964 (Box-folder 101: 7)
    - Foreign aid, article by Reed Irvine, 1958 (Box-folder 101: 8)
    - Miscellaneous, 1965-1967 (Box-folder 101: 9)
  - United States Comptroller, transcripts of reports of 1865-1875 (Box-folder 101: 10)
  - United States. Department of Commerce. Bureau of the Census, forms and instructions to enumerators, undated (Box-folder 101: 11)
  - United States. Department of the Treasury, 1945-1946 (Box-folder 101: 12)
    Correspondence, memoranda, studies, and reports.
  - University of Minnesota, clippings, 1946 (Box-folder 101: 13)
- Audio-Visual File, 1969-1988 (Boxes 102-107)
  Videocassettes and sound recordings of speeches, interviews, conversation transcripts, and television appearances, arranged by physical form. There are additional sound recordings in boxes 235-236.
  - Videocassettes of television appearances
    - Phil Donahue Show, 1980 (Box 102)
      Access
      Use copy reference number: 77011_v_0002243
      Friedman discusses the Hoover Institution, the New Deal, government regulation of the auto industry, and capitalism.
    - Nightline (on the semiconductors international market), 1987 March 17 (Box 102)
  - Sound recordings of speeches, interviews, conversation transcripts, and dictation, 1961-1988; 19.0 Cassettes
    - Telephone talk to the Mont Pélerin Society regional meeting in Rockford, Illinois, 1971 August (Box 102)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0002068
      Friedman analyzes where the world is in the pull between collectivism and individualism. Focusing on the world of ideas, he begins by noting the world of affairs. With a nod to Hayek's The Road to Serfdom, he says the world is less far down the road than how he and Hayek expected the world to be in 1971 when the book was first published. In the world of ideas, he begins by noting a recent renewed upsurge against the market and toward collectivism. Believing the experiences since the book have confirmed Hayek's predictions and opinions, he cites East/West Germany and Berlin as proof.
      Friedman spends most of his time speculating as to why intellectuals tend toward collectivism. Though he admits he has not researched for concrete proof, he analyzes theories as to how intellectuals' self-interest leads them to this disposition. He believes it is counter-intuitive, as there is an incredible stake that intellectuals have in the free market of ideas for themselves. However, he believes the main reason is that there is a larger demand/market for collectivist ideas than individualist ideas, citing the boom in intellectual jobs as part of the New Deal. Friedman says the argument for collectivism is a simple, but compelling devil argument: bad people are doing bad things, so give me the power to stop them. Saying intellectuals believe they are smarter than others, they think they will be the ones given power over the bad guys. He laments that there is no natural law forcing promises to be upheld.
      The market for individualist ideas, however, is much smaller to Friedman, who says it is a more complex idea, where one cannot easily see an invisible hand working. The Mont Pélerin Society does not go collectivist because of this smaller market. As an aside, Friedman also wonders why the mass media is overwhelmingly collectivist, despite individualist slogans, and why they want to use the government as a tool to fulfill these individualist slogans.
    - "Redressing the Excesses of Keynesianism" (or "Free to Choose"), 1980 July 10 (Box 102)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0002061
      This speech was given as part of a conference titled "HANDS ON! HANDS OFF! Should Government Call the Shots or Let the Economic World Unfold?" Friedman speaks on inflation and declining/slow economic growth. Arguing the two as interlinked, he says they are common consequence of government growth: extensions of collectivism overwhelming individualism. He claims energy prices exacerbated both problems, but problems existed before the energy crisis. On inflation, Friedman says it is entirely made by government policy by increasing the net quantity of money. He says it introduces static in market processes and therefore retards economic growth. He believes price and wage controls address the symptoms, but not the causes of inflation. He argues restraining monetary growth is the cure for inflation. Similarly on slow economic growth, he argues it is caused by an over-governed society where there is too much spending and too much regulation. This, in turn, increases inflation according to Friedman.
      In his introductory remarks, he labels himself a radical liberal, one in favor of getting to the roots of human freedom. He says there is no such thing as public capital; government capital is capital extracted from private individuals. He would prefer to discuss "governmental" versus private as opposed to "public" versus private. In the question-and-answer session, Friedman discusses tax cuts in America, foreign capital within Canada and beyond, the steel industry in America, Art Laffer, and critiques the Thatcher government in the UK, saying the policies are generally good, but working too slowly.
    - Summing up and a chance for rebuttal, undated (Box 102)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0004910
    - Senator Joseph Clark debating Milton Friedman and Milton Friedman speech "Planning" given at Earlham College, 1961 (Box 102)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0004909
      The debate is dated 1961 and concerns the proper role of the federal government. Senator Clark favors an unemotional appraisal issue-by-issue; Friedman favors a small government using a critique of Kennedy's inaugural address as his theme. After each man delivers his opening remarks, questions are posed by editors from the Christian Science Monitor and Newsweek. The sound quality of both recordings is poor.
    - Untitled, 1969 June 12 (Box 102)
    - Instructional Dynamics Inc. Information Cassette Series, 1969 June 12 (Box 102)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0004912
      William Clark of the Chicago Tribune interviews Milton Friedman about economic matters.
    - Untitled, 1971 October 12 (Box 102)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0004921
    - Milton Friedman and Friedrich Hayek at Mont Pélerin, Switzerland, during the Mont Pélerin meeting held at Montreux, Switzerland, 1972 (Box 102)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0004934
    - "The Future of Capitalism,", 1977 February 9 (Box 102)
      Use copy reference number: 77011_a_0004938
      Friedman delivered this speech at the Pepperdine University Associates banquet.